<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="chap-installation">

<title>Installation</title>

<para>Charon runs on Linux and Mac OS X.  (It may also run on other
platforms; the main prerequisite is that Nix runs on your
platform.)  Installing it requires the following steps:</para>

<orderedlist>

  <listitem><para>Install the Nix package manager.  You need at least
  version 1.0.  It’s available from the <link
  xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix/download.html">Nix website</link>
  in binary form for several platforms.  Please refer to the <link
  xlink:href="http://hydra.nixos.org/view/nix/trunk/latest/tarball/download-by-type/doc/manual#chap-installation">installation
  instruction</link> in the Nix manual for more
  details.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Obtain the NixOS and Nixpkgs sources and add them to
  <envar>NIX_PATH</envar> environment variable so that Charon can find
  them.  The easiest way to do this is to use the NixOS channel, which
  also ensures that you get pre-built binaries so that your machine
  doesn’t have to compile everything locally:

<screen>
$ nix-channel --add http://nixos.org/releases/nixos/channels/nixos-unstable
$ export NIX_PATH=/nix/var/nix/profiles/per-user/root/channels/nixos
</screen>

  (You may have to replace <literal>root</literal> in the last line by
  your own user name if you’ve installed Nix under another user
  account.)</para>

  <para>Alternatively, you can check out the sources using Git:

<screen>
$ cd /some/dir
$ git clone git://github.com/NixOS/nixos.git
$ git clone git://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs.git
$ export NIX_PATH=/some/dir
</screen>

  In this case you’ll probably want to do

<screen>
$ nix-pull http://nixos.org/releases/nixos/channels/nixos-unstable/MANIFEST
</screen>

  to tell Nix to use the pre-built binaries in the
  <literal>nixos-unstable</literal> channel.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Install the latest version of Charon.  One way to do
  this is to get Charon’s source from Git and build it:

<screen>
$ git clone git://github.com/NixOS/charon.git
$ cd charon
$ nix-env -f . -i charon
$ charon --version
Charon 0.1
</screen>

  Another way is to install the <link
  xlink:href="http://hydra.nixos.org/job/charon/master/build/latest-for/x86_64-linux">latest
  build</link>, e.g.

<screen>
$ nix-install-package --non-interactive --url http://hydra.nixos.org/build/2662145/nix/pkg/charon-0.1pre225_721cf08-x86_64-linux.nixpkg
</screen>

  </para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

<para>FIXME: document how to set up distributed builds on Mac OS X.
This is necessary because Charon builds and deploys Linux (NixOS)
machines and Macs cannot natively do Linux builds.</para>

<para>FIXME: VirtualBox configuration (vboxnet0 host-only networking
interface).</para>

</chapter>
