<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="chap-introduction">

<title>Introduction</title>

<para>NixOps is a tool for deploying NixOS machines in a network or
cloud.  It takes as input a declarative specification of a set of
“logical” machines and then performs any necessary steps actions to
realise that specification: instantiate cloud machines, build and
download dependencies, stop and start services, and so on.  NixOps has
several nice properties:</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>It’s <emphasis>declarative</emphasis>: NixOps
  specifications state the desired configuration of the machines, and
  NixOps then figures out the actions necessary to realise that
  configuration.  So there is no difference between doing a new
  deployment or doing a redeployment: the resulting machine
  configurations will be the same.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It performs <emphasis>fully automated</emphasis>
  deployment.  This is a good thing because it ensures that
  deployments are reproducible.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It performs provisioning.  Based on the given
  deployment specification, it will start missing virtual machines,
  create disk volumes, and so on.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It’s based on the <link
  xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix/">Nix package manager</link>, which
  has a <emphasis>purely functional</emphasis> model that sets it
  apart from other package managers.  Concretely this means that
  multiple versions of packages can coexist on a system, that packages
  can be upgraded or rolled back atomically, that dependency
  specifications can be guaranteed to be complete, and so on.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It’s based on <link
  xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nixos/">NixOS</link>, which has a
  declarative approach to describing the desired configuration of a
  machine.  This makes it an ideal basis for automated configuration
  management of sets of machines.  NixOS also has desirable properties
  such as (nearly) atomic upgrades, the ability to roll back to
  previous configurations, and more.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It’s <emphasis>multi-cloud</emphasis>.  Machines in
  a single NixOps deployment can be deployed to different target
  environments.  For instance, one logical machine can be deployed to
  a local “physical” machine, another to an automatically instantiated
  Amazon EC2 instance in the <literal>eu-west-1</literal> region,
  another in the <literal>us-east-1</literal> region, and so on.
  NixOps arranges the necessary network configuration to ensure that
  these machines can communicate securely with each other (e.g. by
  setting up encrypted tunnels).</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It supports <emphasis>separation of “logical” and
  “physical” aspects</emphasis> of a deployment.  NixOps
  specifications are modular, and this makes it easy to separate the
  parts that say <emphasis>what</emphasis> logical machines should do
  from <emphasis>where</emphasis> they should do it.  For instance,
  the former might say that machine X should run a PostgreSQL database
  and machine Y should run an Apache web server, while the latter
  might state that X should be instantiated as an EC2
  <literal>m1.large</literal> machine while Y should be instantiated
  as an <literal>m1.small</literal>.  We could also have a second
  physical specification that says that X and Y should both be
  instantiated as VirtualBox VMs on the developer’s workstation.  So
  the same logical specification can easily be deployed to different
  environments.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It uses a single formalism (the Nix expression
  language) for package management and system configuration
  management.  This makes it very easy to add ad hoc packages to a
  deployment.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It combines system configuration management and
  provisioning.  Provisioning affects configuration management: for
  instance, if we instantiate an EC2 machine as part of a larger
  deployment, it may be necessary to put the IP address or hostname of
  that machine in a configuration file on another machine.  NixOps
  takes care of this automatically.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>It can provision non-machine cloud resources such as
  Amazon S3 buckets and EC2 keypairs.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>This manual describes how to <link
linkend="chap-installation">install NixOps</link> and how to <link
linkend="chap-overview">use it</link>.  The appendix contains a copy
of the NixOps manual page, which is also available by running
<command>man nixops</command>.</para>

</chapter>
