<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<title>NixOps Release Notes</title>


<!--==================================================================-->

<section xml:id="ssec-relnotes-1.2"><title>Release 1.2 (April 30, 2014)</title>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>General</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>NixOps now requires NixOS 13.10 and up.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Add <code>--all</code> option to <code>nixops destroy</code>, <code>nixops 
      delete</code> and <code>nixops ssh-for-each</code>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The <code>-d</code> option now matches based on prefix for convenience
      when the specified uuid/id is not found.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Resources can now be accessed via direct reference, i.e. you can use
      <code>securityGroups = [ resources.ec2SecurityGroups.foo ];</code> in stead of 
      <code>securityGroups = [ resources.ec2SecurityGroups.foo.name ];</code>.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Changed default value of <code>deployment.storeKeysOnMachine</code> to false, 
      which is the more secure option. This can prevent unattended reboot from finishing, as keys will
      need to be pushed to the machine.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Amazon EC2</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Support provisioning of elastic IP addresses.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Support provisioning of EC2 security groups.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Support all HVM instance types.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Support <code>ap-southeast-1</code> region.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Better handling of errors in pushing Route53 records.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Support using ARN's for applying instance profiles to EC2 instances. This 
      allows cross-account API access.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Base HVM image was updated to allow using all emphemeral devices.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Instance ID is now available in 
      nix through the <code>deployment.ec2.instanceId</code> option, set by nixops.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
      Support independent provisioning of EBS volumes. Previously, EBS volumes could only be
      created as part of an EC2 instance, meaning their lifetime was tied to the instance and 
      they could not be managed separately.  Now they can be provisioned independently, e.g.:

      <programlisting>
      resources.ebsVolumes.bigdata =
        { name = "My Big Fat Data";
          region = "eu-west-1";
          zone = "eu-west-1a";
          accessKeyId = "...";
          size = 1000;
        };
      </programlisting>
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>To allow cross-account API access, the <emphasis>deployment.ec2.instanceProfile</emphasis>
      option can now be set to either a name (previous behaviour) or an Amazon Resource Names (ARN) of the
      instance profile you want to apply.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Hetzner</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Always hard reset on destroying machine.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Support for Hetzner vServers.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Disabled root password by default.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Fix hard reset for rebooting to rescue mode.. This is particularly useful
      if you have a dead server and want to put it in rescue mode. Now it's possible to do that
      simply by running:
    
      <programlisting>
      nixops reboot --hard --rescue --include=deadmachine
      </programlisting>
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>VirtualBox</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Require VirtualBox >= 4.3.0.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Support for shared folders in VirtualBox. You can mount host folder on the guest by setting the 
      deployment.virtualbox.sharedFolders option.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Allow destroy if the VM is gone already</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>


</itemizedlist>

<para>
  This release has contributions from aszlig, Corey O'Connor, Domen Kožar, Eelco Dolstra,
  Michael Stone, Oliver Charles, Rickard Nilsson, Rob Vermaas, Shea Levy and Vladimir Kirillov.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="ssec-relnotes-1.1.1"><title>Release 1.1.1 (October 2, 2013)</title>

<para>This a minor bugfix release.</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>Added a command-line option <emphasis>--include-keys</emphasis> to allow
  importing SSH public host keys, of the machines that will be imported, to the 
  <emphasis>.ssh/known_hosts</emphasis> of the user.
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Fixed a bug that prevented switching the <emphasis>deployment.storeKeysOnMachine</emphasis>
  option value.
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>On non-EC2 systems, nixops will generate ecdsa SSH host keypairs 
  in stead of dsa from now on.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>VirtualBox deployments use generated SSH host keypairs.
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>For all machines which nixops generates an SSH host keypair for, it
  will add the SSH public host key to the known_hosts configuration of all machines
  in the network.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>For EC2 deployments, if the nixops expression specifies a set of
  security groups for a machine that is different from the security groups applied to
  the existing machine, it will produce a warning that the change cannot be made.
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>For EC2 deployments, disks that are not supposed to be attached to the
  machine are detached only after system activation has been completed. Previously this
  was done before, but that could lead to volumes not being able to detach without
  needing to stop the machine.
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Added a command-line option <emphasis>--repair</emphasis> as a convient
  way to pass this option, which allows repairing of broken or changed paths in the nix store,
  to nix-build calls that nixops performs. Note that this option only works in nix setups
  that run without the nix daemon.
  </para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

<para>
  This release has contributions from aszlig, Ricardo Correia, 
  Eelco Dolstra, Rob Vermaas.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="ssec-relnotes-1.1"><title>Release 1.1 (September 9, 2013)</title>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>Backend for <link
  xlink:href="http://hetzner.de">Hetzner</link>, a German data center
  provider. More information and a demo video can be found <link
  xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixops/pull/119">here</link>.
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>When using the <code>deployment.keys.*</code> options, the
  keys in /run/keys are now created with mode 600.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Fixed bug where EBS snapshots name tag was overridden by the
  instance name tag.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>The nixops executable now has the default OpenSSH from nixpkgs
  in its PATH now by default, to work around issues with left-over SSH master
  connections on older version of OpenSSH, such as the version that is installed
  by default on CentOS.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>A new resource type has been introduced to generate sets of SSH
  public/private keys.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Support for spot instances in the EC2 backend. By specifying
    the <code>deployment.ec2.spotInstancePrice</code> option for a machine,
    you can set the spot instance price in cents. NixOps will wait 10
    minutes for a spot instance to be fulfilled, if not, then it will error
    out for that machine.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>


</section>

<section xml:id="ssec-relnotes-1.0.1"><title>Release 1.0.1 (July 11, 2013)</title>

<para>This is a minor bugfix release.</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>Reduce parallelism for running EC2 backups, to
  prevent hammering the AWS API in case of many
  disks.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Propagate the instance tags to the EBS volumes
  (except for Name tag, which is overriden with a detailed description
  of the volume and its use).</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>


</section>

<section xml:id="ssec-relnotes-1.0"><title>Release 1.0 (June 18, 2013)</title>

<para>Initial release.</para>

</section>


</article>
